A Guide to the Withers Family Papers, 1855-1954, Undated
Special Collections, Kegley Library, Wytheville Community College
Special Collections, Kegley Library, Wytheville Community College
Withers Family Papers 1855-1954, Undated
Special Collections, Kegley Library
1997.1
317 folders.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Donated by Gary Laing and Ann Laing in 1997.
Biographical Information
Robert Enoch Withers
Robert Enoch Withers, son of Robert Walter Withers and Susan Dabney Alexander Withers, was born on 18 September 1821 at Rock Castle in Campbell County, Virginia. Withers followed his father's footsteps by becoming a physician; he graduated from the University of Virginia with a medical degree and trained at the Baltimore Almshouse Hospital.
He married Mary Virginia Royall on 3 February 1846; she was the daughter of Joseph Edwin Royall and Mary Elizabeth Royall of Lynchburg, Virginia. The young couple settled in Campbell County where he practiced medicine. During their sojourn in that county, Mary Virginia Royall Withers gave birth to seven daughters including Elizabeth Royall Withers (1846-1927)(married Edwin Lewis Carter), Susan Dabney Withers (1848-1924)(married Henry S. Williams), Alice Chinn Withers (1850-1892)(married Edmund Pendleton Goggins), Jennett Ann Withers (1851-1945)(married 1) Henry Cook 2) Major Waller Boyd), Mary Virginia Withers (1853-1855), Josephine Withers (1854-1956)(married John T. Read), and Kate Massie Withers (1856-1911)(married G. Woodville Smith) at the Briery in Campbell County.
Faced with limited educational opportunities for his growing family, Withers eagerly accepted the advice of his brother Dr. Edward D. Withers and moved to Danville in August 1858. He joined the practice of his brother, sent his girls to school at the Danville Female Academy headed by Rev. George Washington Dame, and purchased a house on Wilson Street.
Children born in Danville include Betty Ellison Withers (1858-1918)(married Stephen Putney), Willie Clare Withers (1859-1939), Virginia Secessia Withers (1861-1939)(married John Young Terry), Robert Edwin Withers (1865-1952)(married Mary Cloyd Kent), and Mary Thornhill Withers (1867-1874).
When the Civil War erupted in 1861, Robert Enoch Withers joined the Confederate Army as a major; he later became colonel of the 18th Virginia Infantry Regiment until he was wounded at the Battle of Gaines Mill. He subsequently oversaw Confederate prisons and hospitals at Danville, Virginia until the war's end.
Withers served as lieutenant-governor of Virginia in 1873. In 1875 he served as a United States Senator for one term. In 1885 President Grover Cleveland appointed him as Consul to Hong Kong. Withers and some of his family members, including Robert Edwin Withers, journeyed to Hong Kong where they stayed for four years.
Withers moved to Wytheville, Virginia in 1879 and eventually purchased the Ingleside home which his daughter Bettie Ellison Putney later purchased from family members. Robert Edwin Withers Sr. later bought Ingleside from niece Josephine Putney Dame.
After his retirement from politics, Withers remained active in the Episcopal Church and served as Examiner of Records from 1896 to 1907. He died on 21 September 1907.
Robert Edwin Withers Sr.
The eleventh child and only son of Mary Virginia Royall Withers and Robert Enoch Withers, Robert Edwin Withers Sr. was born 13 March 1865 in Danville, Virginia. He attended private schools and the Virginia Military Institute in 1882. At V.M.I., Withers joined Sigmi Chi fraternity. After his graduation in 1885, he served as secretary to his father who was U. S. Consul to Hong Kong.
Withers moved to Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania in 1893 and began a long career at the Pittsburgh Reduction Company which later became the Aluminum Company of America. He served as treasurer and assistant secretary, vice-president of finance, a director, and as senior vice-president.
He married Mary Cloyd Kent on 2 June 1892. The couple had two sons, Robert Edwin Withers Jr., who was born on 1 June 1894, and Kent Cloyd Withers who was born on 28 December 1910.
As his father, Robert Edwin Withers was an active member of the Episcopal Church. He served as a lay reader and vestry member of Calvary Episcopal Church in Pittsburgh for many years.
Withers and his wife purchased Ingleside from Josephine Putney Dame and spent many summers with family members there. Robert Edwin Withers died on 29 December 1952.
Robert Edwin Withers Jr.
Robert Edwin Withers Jr. was born on 1 June 1894. Suffering from various physical and behavioral problems, he attended a sanitarium and school run by Dr. Mary Pogue at Lake Geneva, Wisconsin. he graduated from Yeates Preparatory School in Lancaster, Pennsylvania in 1916 and attended the University of Virginia. When the United States entered World War I, Withers enlisted as a private in the Marine Corps and served guard duty at Grieve, France as a sharpshooter.
He graduated from the University of Pittsburgh in 1922 with a bachelors degree in economics. He studied under Rev. W. A. R. Goodwin at the College of William and Mary in 1927 and the following year entered the Virginia Seminary at Alexandria, Virginia to study for the Episcopal ministry. He was ordained at Emmanuel Church, Glenmore, Buckingham County, Virginia in July 1931. He served parishes in Appomattox, Buckingham, and Cumberland counties and also in Ridgeland and Bluffton, South Carolina.
Robert Edwin Withers Jr. married Frances Glover Haskins on 10 August 1933. Haskins was a school teacher and a native of Buckingham County. They had one daughter, Mary Cloyd Kent Withers, who was born on 28 October 1935. Robert Edwin Withers died in February 1981 and Frances Withers died in October 1989.
Kent Cloyd Withers
Kent Cloyd Withers was born on 29 December 1910 in Parnassus, Pennsylvania. He attended the Arnold School and Storm King School. He graduated from the Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute in Troy, New York and began work at the Aluminum Company of America plant in Alcoa, Tennessee. He married Martha Anne Rogers of Morristown, Tennessee on 24 November 1939. They had two sons, Robert Edwin Withers III, born 20 October 1941) and Kent Cloyd Withers Jr. (born 27 August 1947).
During World War II, Withers and his family moved to Spokane, Washington where he worked at the Trentwood Government aluminum plant. After the end of the war they moved back to Knoxville, Tennessee. Kent Cloyd Withers died in 2000.
Scope and Content
The Withers Family Papers chronicle the lives of several members of the Withers family and Kent family of Wythe County, Virginia, and Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania. Documents of Robert Enoch Withers, his son Robert Edwin Withers, and his wife Mary Cloyd Kent Withers and their children dominate this rich collection. Also included are documents of siblings of Robert Edwin Withers and his wife. Family life, education, the Episcopal Church, the Aluminum Company of America, diplomatic service in Hong Kong, Guatemala, and Russia are among subjects found in these Papers.
Series I, Correspondence (1855-1954, Undated), contains 158 folders of correspondence of the Withers family, Kent family, and their relatives, professional colleagues, and friends. The series is arranged chronologically. Understandably, correspondence between the Withers family and Kent family dominate letters in Series I. Information on family activities, schooling, finances, illnesses, and deaths are recorded. Other families mentioned include the Campbell family, Dame family, Darling family, Putney family, and Read family.
Topics covered in this series include education with the following institutions represented: College of William and Mary, University of Virginia, and Virginia Military Institute. Two college preparatory schools, Storm King Preparatory School (Cornwall-on-Hudson, New York) and Yeates Preparatory School (Lancaster, Pennsylvania) are also covered in this series. Correspondence in this subject is mainly between Robert Edwin Withers Jr. and Kent Cloyd Withers and their parents and friends. Both generations were members of Sigma Chi fraternity.
Religious topics, especially those of the Episcopal Church in Pennsylvania and Virginia, are also included. Other churches covered are Wytheville Presbyterian Church and the Seventh Day Adventist Church.
The Withers and Kent families traveled widely to destinations such as Atlantic City, NJ, Florida, Hollywood, White Sulphur Springs, WV, and other United States cities. Robert Edwin Withers Sr. made an annual pilgrimage to Florida to play golf and often stopped in other southern locations including South Carolina and North Carolina.
Health issues including typhoid fever, Oak Leigh Sanitarium in Lake Geneva, Wis., psychiatry, the 1919 influenza epidemic, and the Frontier Nursing Service founded by Mary Breckinridge in Kentucky are discussed in this series.
Correspondence from foreign countries is also included in this series. Robert Enoch Withers served as U. S. Consul to Hong Kong while William Patton Kent was Consul to Guatemala. Kent's son, Tyler Gatewood Kent, served in U. S. embassies in the Soviet Union and England. He was charged with espionage by British authorities and imprisoned throughout World War II.
Other topics covered in this series include automobiles, horses, and railroads. Business topics include labor disputes including coal mining in Pocahontas, West Virginia, Aluminum Company of America, stocks, and bonds. Wytheville topics include Withers Field, McWane Pool, St. John Episcopal Church, Wytheville Presbyterian Church, photographer Susie Fox, Ingleside, and town Christmas decorations as well as town life and activities.
Series II, Withers Genealogy Book Correspondence and Records (1939-1952, Undated), contains correspondence relating to research and publication of Withers Family of the County Lancaster, England, and of Stafford County, Virginia Establishing the Ancestry of Robert Edwin Withers III, presented by Robert Edwin Withers Sr. and prepared by genealogists Katherine Cox Gottschalk and A. May Osler.
Series III, Genealogical Records (1892-1950, Undated), contains notes and drafts of articles written by Mary Cloyd Kent Withers for her publication Word Sketches of Some of Her Relatives, as well as newspaper clippings on Joseph Gordon Kent, Elizabeth A. P. Kent Darling, Kent Crosby Darling, and Dr. Anna P. Kent. Also included are newspaper clippings, a flyer, and notes regarding arrest of Tyler Gatewood Kent for espionage in England during World War II. Notes and newspapers clippings on the Withers family include obituaries for Alice Withers Goggin, Mary Virginia Royall Withers, Susan Catherine Withers Massie, Robert Enoch Withers, Waller Massie Boyd, Elizabeth Royall Withers Carter, and clippings on Willie Clare Withers, Martha Anne Rogers Withers, Kent Cloyd Withers, Frances Haskins Withers, Robert Enoch Withers' Civil War experience, and naming of Withers Field in Wytheville, Virginia.
Also included in this series are photocopies of newspapers clipping of engagements and weddings including those of: Capt. Rodney Snow Jr. and Mary McKinney Goodson [1945], Stanley F. Reed Jr. and Harriet Dyer [1948], Archibald A. Campbell and Eloise Richberg [1950], Thomas Van Kirk Douglass and Margaret Taylor, Edward C. Fuller and Dorothy Berger Edsall, Frank McCormick Painter Jr. and Constance Verde, Charles O'Ferrall Thompson and Mary Terry, Walter Allison Moore and Mary Helen England, Dr. William Sterry and Dr. N. Bowman Wise, Carlton S. Redmond Jr. and Elizabeth Wight, Samuel Stevens Sands and Elizabeth Dame, George Walton Felker III and Elizabeth Paxton Grant, Thomas Pinckney and Charlotte Miller Kent, Kent Crosby Darling and Nelle Powell Payne, Dr. Robert Lee Payne Jr. and Ruth Tunstall Graham, George Macgill Carter Jr. and Margaret Marshall Darsie.
Photocopies of clippings of obituaries include: Peyton Green, Edmund Fontaine Broun, Edwin Stanton Fickes, George E. Gibbons, Flora Cooke Stuart, Samuel Moorehead Russell, Octavia Reed Parrish, Thyrsa Wealththeow Amos, Ogden M. Edwards Jr., George F. Whitman, William Page Dame, Harvey B. Gaul, and Mrs. Thornson Massie. Photocopies of miscellaneous newspapers on the Aluminum Company of America, the Very Rev. Arthur Barksdale Kinsolving, Emily Kent, Henry Watkins Ellerson, Eugenia J. Ferguson Mada Winters, and Rev. Lauiston L. Scaife also comprise this series.
Series IV, Examiner of Records to the Auditor of Public Accounts - Correspondence and Reports (1896-1907, Undated), contains records of Robert Enoch Withers who served as Examiner of Records for the 15th Judicial District t of Virginia from 1896 to 1907. As such Withers reported and audited claims and debts against the Commonwealth of Virginia for Bland, Carroll, Giles, Grayson, Pulaski, Tazewell, and Wythe counties. The series includes correspondence from guardians, executors, commissioners, and others managing estates or orphans as required by an 4 March 1896 act of the General Assembly to report income and personal property.
The Examiner was required to report money, bonds, notes, stock, capital, capital stock, choses in action, and other evidences of debt, and all other species of personal property and income under the control of receivers, commissioners, or fiduciaries or held subject to the order of the several courts in each county subject to tax by an act approved March 4, 1896 as amended by an act approved 3 March 1898, entitled an act to provide for a method for the better assessment of personal property under the control of fiduciaries and the several courts of the commonwealth. The Examiner of Record for each court district reported to the state Auditor of Public Accounts.
Series V, Religious Records (1912-1943, Undated), contains various materials reflecting the Withers affiliation with the Episcopal Church of the United States. Items included are bulletins (1924-1941, Undated) of the Calvary Episcopal Church at which Robert Edwin Withers Sr. and Mary Cloyd Kent Withers regularly worshipped in Pittsburgh, Pa. Withers served several times as a member of the vestry. Another folder contains three miscellaneous items pertaining to Calvary Episcopal Church including an 1894 newsletter, a booklet honoring World War I veterans, and a 1925 guide to the church buildings. Other items in this series include prayer books, a 1933 bulletin from parishes for which Rev. Robert Edwin Withers Jr. served, and a bulletin for the 1944 ordination service of Rev. Charles O'Ferrall Thompson at St. John's Episcopal Church in Wytheville, Virginia.
Series VI, Legal Records (1883-1938, Undated), contains legal records including wills and lists of assets for the estates of Anastasia Pleasants Kent and her mother Anastasia Pleasants Smith Kent. Also included is a copy of the will of Robert Enoch Withers, agreements between Robert Edwin Withers Jr., and the Arthur F. James company regarding car rental, and a trust deed of Mary Cloyd Kent Withers for support of Ellen Stuart.
Series VII, Financial Records (1896-1953, Undated) contains 54 folders relating to financial records of Robert Enoch Withers, Robert Edwin Withers Sr., Mary Cloyd Kent Withers, and Robert Edwin Withers Jr.. Included are account books, checkbooks, Social Security documents, and records on charitable donations by the Withers family. Tax records include personal property tax receipts, real estate tax receipts, and United State income tax forms.
Also included in this series are bills and receipts from Pittsburgh, Pa. and Wytheville, Va. businesses. Receipts for Wytheville businesses including Bolling and Owens Company, W. H. Bolling, Brown Electric Company, G. S. Bruce and Company, Cregger and Chapman, Kincer-Miller Hardware Company, Owens and Kent Company, Owens and Owens Drugstore, Rider Brothers Company, J. Garland Sexton, and the Wytheville Telephone Company.
Series VIII, Photographs (1912-1943, Undated), contains images of Mary Cloyd Kent Withers, Robert Edwin Withers Jr., Kent Cloyd Withers, and Robert Edwin Withers III. Also included are images of Tyler Gatewood Kent, Mary Terry Thompson as a child, Peggy Dewhurst (friend of Kent Cloyd Withers), Grace Ann Ashman as baby, Brumfield Royall, Don Spiller, and Billy Spiller as children.Photographs of Ingleside, the house of Kent Cloyd Withers in Spokane, Washington, an unidentified woman at Heinz Pier, Atlantic City, N. J. are also included. Several other unidentified photographs also comprise the collection.
Series IX, Miscellaneous Records (1933-1945), contains newsletters of the Aluminum Company of America, booklets on Prohibition and Temperance, and the Waldensians, and school and summer camp records of Robert Edwin Withers Jr. and Kent Cloyd Withers. Also included are lists, addresses, and recipes collected by Mary Cloyd Kent Withers. Materials of Robert Edwin Withers Sr. in this series include a National Geographic membership certificate, a Sigma Chi alumni list for Pittsburgh, Pa., and a program for a dinner in honor of Dr. Wesley Clair Mitchell held by the Pittsburgh Athletic Association.
Contents List
- Correspondence 1855-1954, Undated, 158 folders
  - Folder 1. Correspondence - Robert Enoch Withers - Personal 1862-1901., 12 items. (Series-folder 1:1)
    Correspondents include Mary Virginia Royall Withers, Alice Chinn Withers Goggin, Susan Withers Massie, Robert W. Withers, John Young Terry, Robert Edwin Withers Sr., Raleigh W. Chinn, Bettie Ellison Withers Putney, Jennett Withers Cook Boyd, and Flora Virginia Withers.
  - Folder 2. Correspondence - Robert Enoch Withers - Personal 1902-1906, 13 items. (Series-folder 1:2)
    Correspondents include Robert C. Read, Susan Withers Massie, Annie B. Holt Goggin, H. E. Wood, Robert Edwin Withers Sr., Willie Clare Withers, Flora Withers, Lizzie F. Graham, and Gloria Davis.
  - Folder 3. Correspondence - Robert Enoch Withers - Professional 1899-1900, 14 items. (Series-folder 1:3)
    Correspondents include Bud Topham, W. Y. Hayes and Sons, N. B. Rhuday of Wytheville Woolen and Knitting Mills, J. W. Wood and Brothers, T. Lacy, Robert E. Scott, Rev. Mercer P. Logan, Lorig R. Millen, and George S. Sexton.
  - Folder 4. Correspondence - Robert Enoch Withers - Professional 1901-1907, 11 items. (Series-folder 1:4)
    Correspondents include Elbert Lee Trinkle, George S. Sexton, Charles B. Thomas, Simon Kelly, J. C. Wysor, Huff, Andrews, and Moyler Company, G. V. Litchfield, J. M. Spewelt, and H. E. Moore.
  - Folder 5. Correspondence - Mary Virginia Royall Withers 1884-1899, 4 items. (Series-folder 1:5)
    Correspondents include John L. Winchester, David S. Peirce, and Robert Edwin Withers.
  - Folder 6. Correspondence - Anastasia Pleasants Smith Kent 1912-1928, 17 items. (Series-folder 1:6)
    Correspondents include Mary Cloyd Kent Withers.
  - Folder 7. Correspondence - Anastasia Pleasants Smith Kent. 1929-1930, Undated, 17 items. (Series-folder 1:7)
  - Folder 8. Correspondence - Robert Edwin Withers - Personal - to Mary Cloyd Kent Withers 1901-1912, 19 items. (Series-folder 1:8)
  - Folder 9. Correspondence - Robert Enoch Withers - Personal - to Mary Cloyd Kent Withers 1914-1929, 8 items. (Series-folder 1:9)
  - Folder 10. Correspondence - Robert Edwin Withers - Personal - to Mary Cloyd Kent Withers 1930-1937, 20 items. (Series-folder 1:10)
  - Folder 11. Correspondence - Robert Edwin Withers - Personal - to Mary Cloyd Kent Withers 1938, 10 items. (Series-folder 1:11)
  - Folder 12. Correspondence - Robert Edwin Withers - Personal - to Mary Cloyd Kent Withers 1939, 11 items. (Series-folder 1:12)
  - Folder 13. Correspondence - Robert Edwin Withers - Personal - to Mary Cloyd Kent Withers 1940, 13 items. (Series-folder 1:13)
  - Folder 14. Correspondence - Robert Edwin Withers - Personal - Mary Cloyd Kent Withers February - August 1941, 9 items. (Series-folder 1:14)
  - Folder 15. Correspondence - Robert Edwin Withers - Personal - to Mary Cloyd Kent Withers September - October 1941, 10 items. (Series-folder 1:15)
  - Folder 16. Correspondence - Robert Edwin Withers - Personal - to Mary Cloyd Kent Withers 1942, 12 items. (Series-folder 1:16)
  - Folder 17. Correspondence - Robert Edwin withers - Personal - to Mary Cloyd Kent Withers 1943-1948, 10 items. (Series-folder 1:17)
  - Folder 18. Correspondence - Robert Edwin Withers - Personal - Elizabeth Royall Withers Carter 1921-1925, 5 items. (Series-folder 1:18)
  - Folder 19. Correspondence - Robert Edwin Withers - Personal - Jennet Ann Withers Cook Boyd 1931-1934, Undated, 6 items. (Series-folder 1:19)
  - Folder 20. Correspondence - Robert Edwin Withers - Personal - Virginia Secessia Withers Terry 1935-1938, 4 items. (Series-folder 1:20)
  - Folder 21. Correspondence - Robert Edwin Withers - Personal - Josephine Putney Dame 1919-1952, 6 items. (Series-folder 1:21)
  - Folder 22. Correspondence - Robert Edwin Withers - Personal - Virginia Withers Ast 1951-1952, 9 items. (Series-folder 1:22)
  - Folder 23. Correspondence - Robert Edwin Withers - Personal - Cleaveland J. Campbell 1942-1952, Undated, 11 items. (Series-folder 1:23)
  - Folder 24. Correspondence - Robert Edwin Withers - Personal - Clarence J. Kitner 1942-1950, 12 items. (Series-folder 1:24)
    Re: maintenance of Ingleside, house in Wytheville, Virginia.
  - Folder 25. Correspondence - Robert Edwin Withers - Personal - Mary Terry Thompson 1937-1952, Undated, 15 items. (Series-folder 1:25)
  - Folder 26. Correspondence - Robert Edwin Withers - Personal 1879-1927, 14 items. (Series-folder 1:26)
    Correspondents include: Mary Virginia Royall Withers, Carrie Royall Thomas, Betty Ellison Withers Putney, Faye Walter M. Pintard, B. B. Royall, Willie Clare Withers, Rt. Rev. Cortland whitehead, Mary Pogue, F. Gardiner, Kate Crosby Darling, and Kent Crosby Darling.
  - Folder 27. Correspondence - Robert Edwin Withers - Personal 1933-1936, 17 items. (Series-folder 1:27)
    Correspondents include: Alvah K. Lawrie, Seth G. Malby, Joseph Cloyd Kent, Alice W. Merryman, John Royall Read, Mrs. Harry Graham Robinson, W. M. Gifford, C. Chapman, Robert B. Hill, Robert L. Peirce, and John Royall Read Jr.
  - Folder 28. Correspondence - Robert Edwin Withers - Personal 1937-1939, 23 items. (Series-folder 1:28)
    Correspondents include: Katherine Smith Hancock, Bird Carter, Horace B. Horton, Susie Williams Poindexter, Flora Lee Smith, Sam J. Simmons, Joe Manly, Carrie Royall Thomas, Thomas Pinckney, Sallie B. Davis, John C. Hagan Jr., R. W. Massie, Roy A. Hunt, E. M. Payne, William Robinson Terry, and Vincent Matthews Jr.
  - Folder 29. Correspondence - Robert Edwin Withers - Personal 1940-1942, 22 items. (Series-folder 1:29)
    Correspondents include: Rose Carter, Flora Lee Smith, Samuel Graham, Henry S. Hohman, Claude A. Rogers, Don Spiller, Anne H. Patrick Kent regarding charge of espionage against her son Tyler Gatewood Kent, Cleaveland J. Campbell, Carrie Royall Thomas, James W. Rickey, Elizabeth Royall Carter Layman, Paul J. Urquhart, Safford K. Colby, Roy A. Hunt, Alice Kennon Williams Gravely, Mary Kent Withers, and Lowell Innes.
  - Folder 30. Correspondence - Robert Edwin Withers - Personal 1943-1945, 27 items. (Series-folder 1:30)
    Correspondents include: Lucy M. Rickey, Robert Sanger, Bessie Gordon Jones, Martha Massie, William Terry, Robert L. Peirce, Fred A. Thoughton, E. Blough, Sallie Read, W. Bedford Moore Jr., Don Spiller Jr., S. J. Simmons, W. M. Gifford, E. F. Snead, Penn L. Withers, George O. Morgan, G. L. Nicolson, Robert Read, Kent Crosby Darling, and Garnett Brooke Lawson.
  - Folder 31. Correspondence - Robert Edwin Withers - Personal 1946-1949, 29 items. (Series-folder 1:31)